I want to share with you
أريد أن أشارككم
some ideas about the secret power of time,
بعض الأفكار عن القوة السربة للوقت،
in a very short time.
في مدة قصيرة.
Video: All right, start the clock please. 30 seconds studio.
فيديو: حسناً، إبدأ الساعة من فضلك. 30 ثانية أستديو.
Keep it quiet please. Settle down.
إلزموا الصمت من فضلكم.هدوء.
It's about time. End sequence. Take one.
حان الوقت. مشهد النهاية. أول مرة.
15 seconds studio.
أستديو 15 ثانية.
10, nine, eight, seven,
عشرة، تسعة، ثمانية، سبعة
six, five, four, three, two ...
ستة، خمسة، أربعة، ثلاثة، أثنان ...
Philip Zimbardo: Let's tune into the conversation
فيليب زيمباردو: دعونا نبدأ مناقشة
of the principals in Adam's temptation.
المباديء في إغواء أدم.
"Come on Adam, don't be so wishy-washy. Take a bite." "I did."
هيا يا أدم، خذ قضمة، لا تكن متخاذلاَ .. أنا أخذت
"One bite, Adam. Don't abandon Eve."
قضمة واحدة يا أدم .... لا تتخلي عن حواء
"I don't know, guys.
لا أعلم يا رفاق.
I don't want to get in trouble."
لا أريد أن أقع في مشاكل.
"Okay. One bite. What the hell?"
حسناَ، قضمة واحدة، لا شيء يهم؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Life is temptation. It's all about yielding, resisting,
الحياة إغواء. أنها عبارة عن إستسلام ومقاومة،
yes, no, now, later, impulsive, reflective,
نعم، لا، الأن، فيما بعد، تصرفات عفوية أو ردود أفعال،
present focus and future focus.
تركيز علي الحاضر و تركيز علي المستقبل.
Promised virtues fall prey to the passions of the moment.
الفضائل المأمولة تقع فريسة لرغبات اللحظة.
Of teenage girls who pledged sexual abstinence and virginity until marriage --
الفتيات المراهقات اللاتي وعدن بالامتناع الجنسي والعذرية حتي الزواج--
thank you George Bush --
شكراَ لجورج بوش--
the majority, 60 percent, yielded to sexual temptations within one year.
الأغلبية، 60%، إستسلموا للإغرائات الجنسية في خلال عام واحد.
And most of them did so without using birth control.
وأغلبهم فعلوا ذلك دون إستخدام موانع للحمل.
So much for promises.
وعودوهم لم تجدي نفعاً.
Now lets tempt four-year-olds, giving them a treat.
الأن دعونا نغوي أطفالاً في الرابعة من العمر بإعطائهم قطعة حلوي.
They can have one marshmallow now. But if they wait
يستطيعون أخذ قطعة واحدة الأن. لكن إذا إنتظروا
until the experimenter comes back, they can have two.
حتي يعود الشخص الذي يجري التجربة، يستطيعون أخذ إثنان
Of course it pays, if you like marshmallows, to wait.
بالطبع فإنه من المجدي، إذا كنت تحب الحلوي، أن تنتظر.
What happens is two-thirds of the kids give in to temptation.
ما يحدث أن ثلثي الأطفال يستسلموا للإغراء.
They cannot wait. The others, of course, wait.
لا يستطيعون الإنتظار. الأخرين، بالطبع، ينتظرون.
They resist the temptation. They delay the now for later.
إنهم يقاومون الإغراء. ويؤجلون ما يريدون الان لما بعد.
Walter Mischel, my colleague at Stanford,
والتر ميشيل، زميلي في ستانفورد،
went back 14 years later,
عاد بعد 14 عام.
to try to discover what was different about those kids.
لمحاولة إكتشاف ما هو الشىء المختلف في هولاء الأطفال.
There were enormous differences between kids who resisted
كانت هناك فروق هائلة بين الأطفال الذين قاوموا
and kids who yielded, in many ways.
والأطفال الذين إستسلموا، في عدة أشكال.
The kids who resisted scored 250 points higher on the SAT.
الأطفال الذين قاوموا أحرزوا 250 نقطة أعلي في إختبار الـ SAT.
That's enormous. That's like a whole set of different IQ points.
هذا هائل. هذا يماثل مستوي كامل مختلف من مستويات درجات إختبار الذكاء.
They didn't get in as much trouble. They were better students.
لم يقعوا في إي مشاكل. كانوا طلابا أفضل.
They were self-confident and determined. And the key for me today,
كانوا واثقون من أنفسهم و ذوي إصرار. والمهم بالنسبة لي اليوم،
the key for you,
والمهم لكم،
is, they were future-focused rather than present-focused.
أنهم كانوا يركزون علي المستقبل بدلا من التركيز علي الحاضر.
So what is time perspective? That's what I'm going to talk about today.
إذاً ماهو منظور الزمن؟ هذا ما سوف أتحدث عنه اليوم.
Time perspective is the study of how individuals,
منظور الزمن هو دراسة طريقة الأفراد،
all of us, divide the flow of your human experience
كلنا، في تقسيم تجاربنا الأنسانية
into time zones or time categories.
إلي مناطق زمنية أوفئات زمنية.
And you do it automatically and non-consciously.
وأنتم تفعلون ذلك بطريقة أوتوماتيكية وبلا وعي.
They vary between cultures, between nations,
أنها تتفاوت بين الثقافات وبين الأمم،
between individuals, between social classes,
بين الأفراد، بين الطبقات الإجتماعية،
between education levels.
بين مستويات التعليم.
And the problem is that they can become biased,
و المشكلة أنها من الممكن أن تكون متحيزة.
because you learn to over-use some of them and under-use the others.
لأنك تتعلم أن تفرط في إستخدام بعضها وتقصر في إستخدام البعض الأخر.
What determines any decision you make?
ما الذي يحدد أي قرار تتخذ؟
You make a decision on which you're going to base an action.
أنك تتخذ قرار، وبناءاً عليه ستقوم بفعل.
For some people it's only about what is in the immediate situation,
لبعض الناس الأمر يتعلق فقط بالموقف الحالي،
what other people are doing and what you're feeling.
ماذا يفعل الأخرون ومايشعرون.
And those people, when they make their decisions in that format --
وهؤلاء الناس، عندما يتخذون قراراتهم بهذا الشكل--
we're going to call them "present-oriented,"
سنسميهم "المركزون علي الحاضر"
because their focus is what is now.
لأن تركيزهم علي الوقت الحالي.
For others, the present is irrelevant.
بالنسبة للأخرون، الحاضر غير مهم.
It's always about "What is this situation like that I've experienced in the past?"
دائما الأمر يتعلق بـ "ما وجه الشبه بين الوضع الحالي وبين ما واجهته في الماضي؟"
So that their decisions are based on past memories.
إذاً قرارتهم مبنية علي ذكريات الماضي.
And we're going to call those people "past-oriented," because they focus on what was.
و سنسمي هؤلاء "المركزون علي الماضي" لأنهم يركزون علي ما كان.
For others it's not the past, it's not the present,
بالنسبة لأخرين الأمر لا يتعلق بالماضي أو الحاضر،
it's only about the future.
أنه يتعلق فقط بالمستقبل.
Their focus is always about anticipated consequences.
تركيزهم دائماً علي عواقب الأمور.
Cost-benefit analysis.
تحليل العائد-التكلفة.
We're going to call them "future-oriented." Their focus is on what will be.
سنطلق عليهم "المركزون علي المستقبل". تركيزهم علي ما سيكون.
So, time paradox, I want to argue,
إذاً المعضلة الزمنية، ما أريد مناقشته،
the paradox of time perspective,
معضلة المنظور الزمني،
is something that influences every decision you make,
هي شيء يؤثر علي كل قرار تتخذه،
you're totally unaware of.
وأنت غير مدرك لها تماماً.
Namely, the extent to which you have one of these
تحديداً، إلي أي درجة لديك
biased time perspectives.
منظورات زمنية متحيزة.
Well there is actually six of them. There are two ways to be present-oriented.
حسناً هناك في حقيقة الأمر ستة منها، هناك نوعان من التركيز علي الحاضر.
There is two ways to be past-oriented, two ways to be future.
هناك نوعان من التركيز علي الماضي، نوعان من التركيز علي المستقبل.
You can focus on past-positive, or past-negative.
يمكنك التركيز علي الماضي الإيجابي أو الماضي السلبي.
You can be present-hedonistic,
يمكنك أن تركز علي الملذات الحالية،
namely you focus on the joys of life, or present-fatalist --
تحديداً أن تركز علي متع الحياة، أو القدرية الحالية.
it doesn't matter, your life is controlled.
لا يهم. حياتك متحكم بها.
You can be future-oriented, setting goals.
يمكنك أن تركز علي المستقبل، وتضع أهداف.
Or you can be transcendental future:
أو يمكنك أن تكون مستقبلي الأفكار:
namely, life begins after death.
تحديداً، الحياة تبدأ بعد الموت.
Developing the mental flexibility to shift time perspectives fluidly
تطوير المرونة العقلية للتحكم فى المنظور الزمنى ينساب
depending on the demands of the situation,
حسب متطلبات الموقف،
that's what you've got to learn to do.
هذا ما يجب عليك أن تتعلمه.
So, very quickly, what is the optimal time profile?
إذا، بسرعةجدا ، ما هو الإطار الزمنى المثالى؟
High on past-positive. Moderately high on future.
تركيز عالي علي الماضي الإيجابي, تركيز عالي معتدل علي المستقبل.
And moderate on present-hedonism.
ومعتدل علي الرغبات الحاضرة.
And always low on past-negative
ودائما أقل علي الماضي السلبي.
and present-fatalism.
والقدرية الحالية.
So the optimal temporal mix is what you get from the past --
إذاً المزيج الزمني الأمثل هو ما تحصل عليه من الماضي --
past-positive gives you roots. You connect your family, identity and your self.
الماضي الإيجابي يعطيك جذورك. تتصل بعائلتك، تحدد ماهيتك.
What you get from the future is wings
ما تحصل عليه من المستقبل هو الأجنحة
to soar to new destinations, new challenges.
لتحلق نحو وجهات جديدة، تحديات جديدة.
What you get from the present hedonism
ما نحصل عليه من القدرية الحالية
is the energy, the energy to explore yourself,
هو الطاقة، الطاقة لإستكشاف نفسك،
places, people, sensuality.
الأماكن، الناس، الملذات الحسية.
Any time perspective in excess has more negatives than positives.
أي منظور يزيد عن ذلك له أثر سلبي أكثر منه إيجابي.
What do futures sacrifice for success?
بماذا يضحي المستقبليون من أجل النجاح؟
They sacrifice family time. They sacrifice friend time.
إنهم يضحون بالوقت المخصص للأسرة.والوقت المخصص للأصدقاء.
They sacrifice fun time. They sacrifice personal indulgence.
إنهم يضحون بالوقت المخصص للمرح والمتع الشخصية.
They sacrifice hobbies. And they sacrifice sleep. So it affects their health.
إنهم يضحون بالهوايات. و يضحون بالنوم. وبالتالي فإن صحتهم تتأثر.
And they live for work, achievement and control.
وإنهم يعيشون للعمل، الإنجاز والسيطرة.
I'm sure that resonates with some of the TEDsters.
أنا واثق أن هذا يحمل معني لـبعض المشاركين بـ TED.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it resonated for me. I grew up as a poor kid in the South Bronx ghetto,
ولي أيضاً. أنا نشأت كطفل فقير في حي فقير بجنوب برونكس.
a Sicilian family -- everyone lived in the past and present.
لعائلة صقلية. الجميع عاشوا في الماضي والحاضر.
I'm here as a future-oriented person
أنا هنا كشخص يركز علي المستقبل
who went over the top, who did all these sacrifices
شخص ذهب إلي أخر المدي، شخص قام بكل هذه التضحيات
because teachers intervened, and made me future oriented.
لأن المدرسون تدخلوا، و جعلوني مركزاً علي المستقبل.
Told me don't eat that marshmallow,
قالو لي لا تأكل الحلوي،
because if you wait you're going to get two of them,
لأنك لو إنتظرت ستحصل علي قطعتين،
until I learned to balance out.
حتي تعلمت أن أوازن الأمور.
I've added present-hedonism, I've added a focus on the past-positive,
أضفت الإستمتاع بالحاضر. أضفت التركيز علي الماضي الإيجابي.
so, at 76 years old, I am more energetic than ever, more productive,
إذاً في الـ 76 من العمر، أنا أنشط من ذي قبل، أكثر أنتاجية،
and I'm happier than I have ever been.
و أكثر سعادة من أي وقت مضي.
I just want to say that we are applying this to many world problems:
أنا فقط أريد أن اقول أننا نطبق هذا علي كثير من مشاكل العالم،
changing the drop-out rates of school kids,
تغيير معدلات رسوب الأطفال فى المدارس،
combating addictions, enhancing teen health,
محاربة الإدمان، تحسين صحة المراهقين،
curing vets' PTSD with time metaphors -- getting miracle cures --
علاج المحاربين القدامي من الصدمات باستخدام أوصاف زمنية -- أتت بشفاءات مذهلة--
promoting sustainability and conservation,
الترويج للبقاء والحفاظ،
reducing physical rehabilitation where there is a 50-percent drop out rate,
التقليل من إعادة التأهيل البدني حيث معدل الانسحاب يصل لـ 50%،
altering appeals to suicidal terrorists,
تغيير رغبة الإرهابيين في المحاولات الإنتحارية،
and modifying family conflicts as time-zone clashes.
وتعديل الخلافات العائلية كتصادمات بين المناطق الزمنية.
So I want to end by saying:
أريد أن أنهي بقول،
many of life's puzzles can be solved
كثير من معضلات الحياة ممكن أن تحل
by understanding your time perspective and that of others.
بفهم منظورك ومنظور الأخرين للزمن.
And the idea is so simple, so obvious,
والفكرة بسيطة جداً، واضحة جداً،
but I think the consequences are really profound.
لكن أنا أعتقدأن العواقب ستكون عميقة بحق.
Thank you so much.
شكراَ جزيلاَ
(Applause)
(تصفيق)